hey Jason flin here and today I'm going
to talk to you about a communication
model that you can use which will help
you close more sales it'll help you have
more impact with whatever content and
education material you create and it
will even improve interpersonal
relationships with friends with loved
ones family members Intimate
Relationships etc etc now before we get
into this communication model that I'm
going to break down here today let's
talk about why it's important and I
think the main reason more than anything
else else is it puts you in a state of
instant Rapport near effortlessly and
the Rapport is very deep at least 34s of
this communication model does there is
1/4 of it that creates intentional
misreport is that a word I don't know it
creates dissonance instead of resonance
I'm a music guy so that's how I think in
terms of the world would be very boring
if we played everything in the scale in
the key and there was no dissonance and
so most of the time incommunication when
to create resonance occasionally
tactically we want to create dissonance
and so I'll break down for you the
three4 of the time we resonate the 1/4
when we intentionally create dissonance
to create further understanding deeper
connection so on and so forth this also
unlocks empathy I think empathy is a
secret weapon my friend Chris Voss
bestselling author of maybe of all time
of the book never split the difference
which is an unbelievable Masterpiece in
its own right I went to his premiere of
his documentary and it was called
tactical empathy he came up with that
name I love it we can use empathy in a
way that is wholesome and ethical and
it's perhaps the best way to really
understand somebody else and then as a
result have them be open to hearing you
because now they feel understood so now
they're more receptive maybe the most
receptive they can be to any insight or
any advice that you can give and lastly
the reason this model works so well is
it helps you break out of stuck patterns
I'm not sure if You' ever heard of the
concept of the shame spiral but it is
one of the most Insidious patterns that
really limit us and harm us as human
beings is we feel bad about something
and then we feel bad about feeling bad
about the thing and now we feel really
miserable which makes us feel even worse
and pretty soon you just go into the
shame spiral where you feel bad about
feeling bad almost in perpetuity and it
ratches it up we are creatures of habit
and our habits are typically
pattern-based and it's really easy when
we hit limiting behavioral patterns to
get stuck in those and to get caught in
ruts so to speak and so this can help
unwedge people people that are stuck in
patterns and even in Communications with
other people where you say this and they
say that and it just happens every
single time a trigger if you will and
then how do you get forward in your
communication you don't and if you
repeat it over and over again you don't
stay stuck actually you get worse you
stay stuck in the pattern but the result
becomes more and more disharmony all
right so let's break down this model on
a high level I always like to think in
terms of macro not just micro but to see
what is the overarching kind of
responses to something or what are the
inputs to something what are the
critical ones and I tend to lean to four
there's a pattern I've just discovered
over and over again where you can almost
break anything down into fours I'm going
to do a YouTube video on the
productivity hack with the 4x4 model and
when it comes to responding to something
if somebody says something to you or if
somebody comes to you looking for
something if somebody offers you
something other either directly where
they say hey this is what I'm feeling
right now or this is what's going on
right now or indirectly if you're
addressing a Marketplace or a produ ECT
and you've observed certain behaviors or
cues and you are addressing that this is
how you can address that there are four
ways and only four ways essentually now
there's multiple colors of these four
ways but the four broad Strokes of it
are you can agree with what they say or
what they think or what they feel or
what they believe you can challenge it
you can reflect it or you can ignore it
now I like to use sales as an example
one it's not too deep and too personal
where it might feel weird if you get
into the weed needs too fast two is I'm
really good at it so I have a really
fundamental understanding of some of the
intricacies of this applied in that one
specific context of sales three we're
all used to sales we're always selling
at all times whether we realize it or
not and we're always buying at all times
what we buy and what we sell obviously
can determine where we go in life and so
this is why I like to use cell as an
example here let's talk about objections
because typically where there is a
disconnection is Created from an
objection I object to what you believe
in or you object to how I show up in the
world and that's what creates that
friction and if we can't get past that
friction and move into understanding
nobody benefits and so a typical
objection in sales is it cost too much
or it's too expensive or I can't afford
it it's a price objection related to
large amount of cost for an unknown
value that may occur in advance or in
exchange for that so in a onetoone
setting if if you were selling a product
and you showed it and you said this is
what it is this is what it does is the
investment to get started in this and
somebody said to you gosh that's a lot
of money the natural salesperson is
likely to respond reflexively or
defensively they want to justify that it
isn't a lot of money the problem with
that type of reactive communication is
at least at an unconscious level it
makes people uneasy like what's this
dude doing feeling insecure about the
price they don't hold a strong frame of
confidence related to what they're
charging and that's a big issue and that
causes that friction potentially
unspoken friction if it's not saying out
loud so by far my favorite way to deal
with a price objection is to agree with
it I like just agree with almost
everything that is my default is to
agree to it so I can better understand
that person at least agree to their
point of view I don't have to adopt it
or adapt it to my own but I can agree
with it nonetheless so if somebody says
yeah it's expensive I say it it is
expensive but is it worth paying the
price for it and I have closed more
sales that way by simply just agreeing
with that objection then I have trying
to fight it trying to counter it trying
to wrestle it away and so on and so
forth and so in communication I find
more often than not the best thing to do
is to agreed right away so kid comes out
of school and she's all upset and she
says I had a terrible day today I say
you had a terrible day today I agree
with her I don't question it I don't
challenge it I don't suggest otherwise I
meet her where she's at and then once
she sees that and feels that then she
feels safe to give me further
information this is the best thing I
ever did with my children is I bought a
book called something along the lines I
think it's called how to talk so kids
will listen and how to listen so kids
will talk one of those things you
reverse that flip it around and you
figure it out you can Google that and
again with my friend Chris Voss is the
same thing when he was dealing with
terrorists he would agree with what they
were saying and terms of reflecting it
back to them active listening if you
will where he'd say you don't believe
that I can you know get you what you're
asking for or something like that along
those lines and so agreement is the most
powerful frame of communication that
there is now you can agree to what
somebody is saying without necessarily
agreeing with the conclusion of it so if
a child comes up to you and say
everybody hates me you can say everybody
hates you and you can agree with their
assessment based on their context and
their Viewpoint in the life that they're
living now without necessarily thinking
well I don't hate you but that's the
reflex isn't it that's what everybody
wants to do is they want to challenge
which is the second model second portion
of the model of communication we're
talking about here youd say I don't hate
you and you know what happens in most
communication when you do that if
somebody says everybody hates me and you
say I don't hate you the tendency is to
push back right so this is like new
every action has an equal and opposite
reaction I think that's new and I'm a
little rusty on my physics is if they
offer this out to to you and you push it
back on them they will push back on you
and that's where miscommunication
happens so it's extremely rare in
communication where you directly should
challenge something immediately now
there are times when challenging makes
sense so this is where we we say
intentionally we're going to create
dissonance to perhaps get a further
understanding in a sales situation if
somebody says it costs too much I might
say it costs a lot but does not buying
cost even more so you challenge it now
think about how I just challenged it
there it wasn't a head-on challenge
often times I like to challenge it
around the edges softly and again with
as much empathy and consideration for
the other individual as possible
somebody says it costs too much I said
it might cost too much to the wrong
person but are you the wrong person are
you the right person it's a disarming
way to challenge so if a child comes to
you and says everybody hates me you can
say everybody hates you and you question
it while saying the same exact thing you
turn the statement into a question and
so again rarely is the answer Challenge
and when it is challenge it's rarely a
direct assault on the challenge uh
unless you intentionally want to repel
somebody and push them away and create a
lot of stress and anxiety which I don't
think you do hopefully not there's also
reflection so this kind of is it's not
agreement wholly it's I need to know
more about what you're saying so I can
understand you better so the first thing
we can do is agree the second thing we
can do is challenge the third thing we
do is reflect and so if somebody comes
to me in a sell situation and they say
it cost too much if I were to reflect
that to them I would say what I'm
hearing is you want to get the best bang
for your buck or another version of that
is I'll say if I understand you
correctly your finances are tight right
now so you want to get the most out of
your finances since you have limited
finances is that correct and I love that
reflecting question because if they say
no that isn't correct they will tell me
more so I can understand them better and
if they say yes that is correct then we
kind of know even more narrowly and more
specifically what we have to hone in on
when we communicate verbally there's a
lot of deletion that occurs and so when
you say a statement somebody hears only
the words but they don't hear the stuff
in between the blanks and what those
words mean to you and all the different
under the iceberg type of communication
that really exists right there so often
times you know somebody takes it out on
you when some other people have been
mean to them throughout the day and you
don't know about any of the other stuff
that's happened to them throughout the
day you take them where they're at and
so when we can reflect on somebody we
can unpack further more what the real
issue is and so if a child comes out and
says everybody hates me what you might
find out through reflection is one
person that day said something mean to
them but that one person is so important
to them that it's coloring how they view
everybody else you can get more narrow
into what's really going on often times
when people first profer up to you when
they're looking for help or looking to
feel safe or just want somebody to talk
to the first thing they profer up to you
is a smoke screen it's a superficial
version of what's really going on and
it's kind of like if you can be in sync
with me I will let you really know
what's going on cuz then I'll feel safe
but otherwise right now I'm feeling in a
vulnerable position and so I have to be
cautious with my communication again
most of this stens on a superficial
level now there is a fourth thing you
can do so you can agree you can
challenge you can refle Factor the
fourth thing is ignoring sometimes
ignoring works really well so in a sell
situation ignoring would be if somebody
says it costs a lot I said here's what
this can do for you and just flat out
pretend I didn't hear what they just
said rule of judgment here is if if this
is really the issue or not you're trying
to figure out if it is or it isn't if
somebody's saying it cost too much it
cost too much it cost too much but
they're still focusing on like oh my God
this thing and that thing and I want to
know about this and I want to know about
that you can say okay that is a lesser
important factor in the decision that
needs to be made made and there are many
factors that I can tell from this person
based on our communication or even
merely through observation on what they
need in order to make a decision that
would be right for them so instead of
getting swept up in the minor things
let's focus more on the major things so
sometimes when they are offering up
minor objections or minor issues you
steer the conversation back to the major
issues so in the case if they're all
price focused you focus on value because
it's not just price or value it's price
related to value and so you got to kind
of tip the scills back in your favor in
those types of communication now here's
the big secret to why U I believe I have
been so successful in marketing when I'm
communicating in Mass I do all four of
those things I agree I challenge I
reflect and I ignore so this is why I
like webinars I might have hundreds and
hundreds of people on so I can in
portions of the webinar agree with
certain things that normally you think
you wouldn't agree with so I might say
to somebody you think that right now
everything that I'm doing today has been
calculated to get you to
buy flat I'll say that H and so I can
agree with them and I say whether that's
the case or not would it still make
sense for you to invest that's what we
need to investigate for example so I can
agree I at certain points I can
challenge for certain individuals I can
reflect and I can ignore so if people
keep coming back to one issue one issue
I can say listen we're going to just put
that to the side right now what we're
going to focus on because I think this
is more important in this moment for you
to look at is this but what's cool is at
an individual level I can hit those
little pockets cuz sometimes people need
an agreement to move forward sometimes
they needed to be challenged to move
forward sometimes they needed to be
reflective so they can unpack it more
and sometimes they can ignore it like a
reflection is often times I I I ask
people I said is it failure that you're
afraid of or is it success that you're
afraid of because here's the things with
failure that you know about so they're
known fears but success maybe they're
unknown fears CU you've never been
successful with this yet what could that
look like and now we allow them to
unpack further more what the real issue
is here and often times they'll say well
it's really about blank you say oh well
we can talk talk about that now I can do
this in Mass on a webinar working with
individuals but then framing it so
everybody in the group listening or
watching the replay can also understand
it and that's really the answer here is
if you layer on different modes of
communication even at an individual
level you're likely to get better
results in terms of the Harmony and
understanding and connection that comes
from that communication and so we will
try all of them we will try to agree we
will try to reflect we'll try to
challenge and we will try to ignore
because the end result is a deeper
understanding of the other individual
most of us at the end of the day we walk
around feeling like we're misunderstood
and that makes us feel alone like nobody
gets us and so if somebody can get us
that makes us feel better about who we
are as individuals it makes us feel
safer and when we feel safer we can do
more amazing things we can live in
abundance and we can Thrive and so the
best thing we can do for everybody else
is to learn how to better communicate
unate at the same time other people will
be more easily able to communicate with
us if we demonstrate that we can
communicate with them so this will help
you in business this will help you when
you're a coach or a trainer this will
just really help you with the people
that you care about to seek better
understanding and from that like we said
abundance becomes even more abundant so
there you go I'll see you in the next
video